Inventory of the United States Army, First Army miscellaneous records
Hoover Institution Archives
United States Army, First Army miscellaneous records
1918-1919
XX309
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes (1.2 linear feet)
Reports, memoranda, orders, and maps, relating to military conditions in France during World War I, the German railway system, and experiences of German and Allied prisoners of war.
United States. Army. Army, 1st.
Access
The collection is open for research. The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Biographical/Historical note
The First Army was established in France in 1918 under the command of General John J. Pershing. The First Army was stationed near Verdun, where it was involved in the Meuse-Argonne offensive and the Battle of Saint-Mihiel. It was deactivated in 1919.
Source: http://www.first.army.mil/
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection is comprised of reports, memoranda, orders, and maps, relating to military conditions in France during World War I, the German railway system, and experiences of German and Allied prisoners of war.
United States. Army. American Expeditionary Forces.; Prisoners of war.; World War, 1914-1918--Campaigns--France.; World War, 1914-1918--Prisoners and prisons.; World War, 1914-1918--Transportation.
- Reports, 1918-1919
  - Data relating to the strength of the First Army, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - German occupation, 1918 August 23 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - American offensive on Verdun Front, 1918 September-October (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Ruses and snares of the enemy when retreating, undated (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Study on concentration of enemy reserves north of Etain, 1918 September (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Possible withdrawal, 1918 October 28 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Headquarter 79th Division, 1918 October-December (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - American aviators captured by the enemy, 1918 November 15 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Report of the functioning of G-2 in the St. Mihiel and Argonne-Meuse operations, 1918 November 18 (Box-folder 1: 9-11)
  - "My experiences in the American army with officers and men" by W. Schmidt, 1918 December 6 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - International living conditions, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Miscellaneous reports and statements, 1918 Feburary-November (Box-folder 1: 14-15)
  - "How Germany Treated American Prisoners" by Van Cise, 1919 April 3 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Translations of German documents, 1919 (Box-folder 1: 17)
- Memoranda, 1918
  - Observations on the administration of military justice, 1918 February 20 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Progress of intelligence work, 1918 September 20 (Box-folder 1: 19)
- Orders, 1918-1919
  - Extract of general orders, no. 4, 1919 January 4 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - General orders, 1918 November 11-December 19 (Box-folder 2: 2-3)
  - Field orders, 1918 August 9-November 21 (Box-folder 2: 4-5)
- Summaries of Intelligence, 1918 August 29-November 11 (Box-folder 2: 6-7)
- "Studies of the German Railroad System and its Capacity for the Movement of Troops, Ammunitions, and Supplies on the Western Front", undated (Box-folder 3: 1)
- Victory telegrams, 1918 November 12 (Box-folder 3: 2)
- Bulletin for intelligence officers, American Expeditionary Forces, G-2, 1918 December 21 (Box-folder 3: 3)
- Rosters, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 4)
- Maps, 1918 (Box-folder 3: 5)
- Statements of captured, escaped, and returning prisoners of war, 1918
  - French escaped prisoners: Arsene Sari and Desire Dubois, 1918 July 11 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Memorandum Number 304, concerning the searching of prisoners captured by the 42nd Division, 1918 September 29 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Russian returning prisoners: Ivan Kalinisck and Alexander Merken, 1918 October 14 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - American returning prisoners, 1918 November (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Statements of Interrogations, 1918 November 12 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Canadian returning prisoner: Joseph Gareau, 1918 December 1 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - French returning prisoner: Marius Garvey, 1918 December 1 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - British returning prisoners: James Liddy, Tieman Carlisle. John F. McDonald, and George Sculpher, 1918 December 1-3 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - Interrogation of escaped Italian prisoner Arturo Fogolini, 1918 December 18 (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - German escaped prisoner: Hans Bettin, 1918 December (Box-folder 3: 15)